A Guide to the St. George Tucker Grinnan Papers, 1716-1885
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
St. George Tucker Grinnan Papers, 1716-1885.
Library of Virginia
23409
178 leaves (positive and negative photostats).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying by St. George Tucker Grinnan, 28 September 1949.
Biographical/Historical Information
St. George Tucker Grinnan was born 6 April 1870, in Madison County, Virginia, to Andrew Glassell Grinnan (1827-1902) and Georgia Screven Bryan Grinnan (1837-1912). He was educated in Madison County schools, then attended the University of Virginia, graduating with a medical degree in 1901. Grinnan practiced medicine until he retired in 1947. He also served as professor of pediatrics at the Medical College of Virginia. Grinnan belonged to several medical associations and wrote several articles for medical journals. He married Susan F. Dabney on 18 April 1906, and they had five children. Grinnan died 10 November 1952, in Richmond, Virginia. He is buried in Hollywood Cemetery in Richmond.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1716-1885, compiled by St. George Tucker Grinnan consisting mainly of the correspondence of John Coalter (1769-1838) of Richmond, Virginia, and John Randolph Bryan (1806-1887) of Georgia and Fluvanna County, Virginia. About two-thirds of the collection is the correspondence to and from Judge Coalter and his family, including his wife, Ann Frances Bland Tucker Coalter (1779-1813) and his father St. George Tucker (1752-1827). Writers comment on political and social events. Other correspondents include John Randolph (1773-1833), William Wirt (1772-1834), Beverley Tucker (1784-1851), and Henry St. George Tucker (1780- 1848).
About one-third of the collection is the correspondence of Bryan to his daughter, Georgia Screven Bryan Grinnan (1837-1912) and her husband, Andrew Glassell Grinnan (1827-1902). These letters comment mostly on Bryan's plantations at Carysbrook in Fluvanna County, and Lafitta in Louisiana, as well as coal mining. Papers also inclue bonds, deeds, land grants, lists of slaves, obituaries, powers of attorney, promissory notes, transcripts, wills, and Bible records for the Bryan and Dabney families.
Contents List
- Bond. George Alves, New Kent County, to George Dabney, King William County, dated 9 October 1716, and recorded New Kent County, 11 October 1716., 3 prints.
- Patent. Four hundred acres in Hanover County to Captain George Dabney, King William County, by Hugh Drysdale, Lieutenant Governor of Virginia, 9 July 1724., 2 prints.
- Will. Mary Barret, Louisa County, dated 3 December 1741, and proved [24 February 1746]., 1 print.
- Power of attorney. Charles Dabney to Benjamin Forsythe, both parties of Hanover County, dated 4 August 1794., 1 print.
- Letter. Frances Bland Coalter, Warm Spring, Bath County, to Mrs. [Frances?] Davenport, near Staunton, 20 September 1809., 1 print.
- Will. Frances Davenport, Augusta County, dated 3 April 1810., 2 prints.
- Letter. Frances Bland Coalter, Staunton, to John Coalter, Richmond, 8 June [1811]., 4 prints.
- Letter. Frances Bland Coalter to Mrs. [Frances?] Davenport, Elm Grove near Staunton, 20 September [1811]., 1 print.
- Letter. St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, Richmond, 11 October 1811., 1 print.
- Letter. Frances Bland Coalter to John Coalter, Richmond, December 1811., 3 prints.
- Letter. St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, Richmond, 9 December 1811., 3 prints.
- Letter. St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, to Mr. and Mrs. Coalter and Mr. and Mrs. Cabell, Richmond, 1 January 1812., 3 prints.
- Letter. John Coalter, to Mrs. [Frances?] Davenport, near Staunton, 15 June 1813., 4 prints.
- Letter. John Randolph, Richmond, to Charles Harris, Savannah, Georgia, 23 February 1814., 2 prints.
  Included is a copy of an obituary notice of Joseph Bryan, dated 5 September 1812, and a copy of a promissory note from Jonathan Bryan to John Baber and Company, 12 April 1757.
- Letter. John Coalter, Richmond, to Mrs. [Frances?] Davenport, near Staunton, 10 May 1814., 1 print.
- Letter. Fancilea Coalter to [?], 17 July 1814., 2 prints.
  Included is a postscript by "J.C."
- Memorandum. St. George Tucker, Warminster, to [?] Coalter, 27 September 1814., 2 prints.
- Letter. St. George Tucker, Warminster, to John Coalter, Richmond, 27 September 1814., 4 prints.
- Letter. [Mary Tucker?], Charlotte, to brother John Coalter, Richmond, 13 October 1814., 5 prints.
- Letter. St. George Tucker, Norfolk, to John Coalter, Richmond, 7 November 1814., 1 print.
- Letter. J. Ranolph to brother, John Coalter, Bush Hill, near Richmond, 3 December 1814., 1 print.
- Letter. St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, Richmond, 26 December 1814., 4 prints.
- Letter. St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, [?] Coalter, 1 March 1815., 1 print.
- Letter. St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, near Richmond, 5 March 1815., 1 print.
- Letter. St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, Bush Hill near Richmond, 6 March 1815., 1 print.
- Letter. St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, Bush Hill near Richmond, 24 April 1815., 1 print.
- Letter. St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, Bush Hill near Richmond, 25 November 1815., 1 print.
- Letter. St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, Bush Hill near Richmond, 1 December 1815., 4 prints.
- Letter. St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, Richmond, 9 December 1815., 4 prints.
- Letter. St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, near Richmond, 20 December 1815., 1 print.
- Letter. St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, near Richmond, 1 January [1816]., 1 print.
- Letter. St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, near Richmond, 9 January 1816., 1 print.
- Letter. John Ranolph, George Town, to Mrs. Judith Randolph, Richmond, 20 January 1816., 3 prints.
- Letter. Henry St. George Tucker to John Coalter, Richmond [? February 1816]., 1 print.
- Letter. St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, Richmond, 21 February 1816., 1 print.
- Letter. Henry St. George Tucker, Washington, to John Coalter, Richmond, 28 February 1816., 1 print.
- Letter. St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, to [Coalter?], 4 March 1816., 1 print.
- Letter. St. George Tucker to John Coalter, Richmond, 15 March 1816(?)., 1 print.
- Letter. William Wirt, Richmond, to [?] Coalter, 27 June 1816., 1 print.
- Letter. Joseph C. Cabell, Edgewood, to Judge Coalter, near Richmond, 1 July 1816., 3 prints.
- Letter. St. George Tucker, Warminster, to John Coalter, Staunton, 22 September 1816., 4 prints.
- Letter. St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, to [?] Coalter, 15 November 1816., s prints.
  Included is a postscript by "L.T."
- Letter. St. George Tucker to John Coalter, 22 March 1817., 2 prints.
- Letter. St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, Bush Hill near Richmond, 26 April 1817., 4 prints.
- Letter. St. George Tucker, Norfolk, to [?] Coalter, 2 May 1819., 1 print.
- Letter. Delia F. Bryan, Nonchelance, Georgia, to John Ranolph, Charlotte Court House, 8 November 1819., 1 print.
- Letter. Henry St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, Richmond, 24 December 1819., 3 prints.
- Letter. B. Tucker, St. Louis, to John Coalter, Richmond, 26 December 1819., 1 print.
- Letter. Dabney Carr, Winchester, to John Coalter, Richmond, 18 February 1820., 3 prints.
- Letter. Henry St. George Tucker to John Randolph, [Washington], 26 April 1824., 1 print.
- Letter. Elizabeth Tucker Coalter, Bush Hill, to John Randolph, Washington, 13 March 1826., 1 print.
- Letter. William Wirt, Washington, to John Coalter, Chatham near Fredericksburg, 11 August 1827., 1 print.
- Letter. John Randolph, Chatham, to Henry Tucker, Winchester, 6 February 1829., 1 print.
- Letter. John Randolph Bryan, Brooklyn, to John Randolph, Richmond, 7 October 1829., 3 prints.
- Letter. John Randolph, Roanoke, to John Randolph Bryan, Eagle Point near Gloucester Court House, 29 July 1832., 1 print.
- Letter. John Randolph, Roanoke, to John Randolph Bryan, Eagle Point near Gloucester Court House, 22 August 1832., 1 print.
- Letter. John Randolph, Philadelphia, to John Randolph Bryan and Elizabeth Tucker Coalter Bryan, 24 May 1824., 1 print.
- Letter. Elizabeth Tucker Bryan, Eagle Point, to Mrs. Tucker, Williamsburg, 24 June 1833., 3 prints.
- Letter. Joseph Bryan, Savannah, to John R. Bryan, Gloucester Court House, 11 December 1835., 3 prints.
- Letter. Elizabeth Tucker Bryan, Eagle Point, to [?], 8 February 1854(?)., 4 prints.
- Letter. John R. Bryan, Boscobel, to Dr. Andrew G. Grinnan, 24 February 1860., 1 print.
- Letter. John R. Bryan, Carysbrook, to Dr. Andrew G. Grinnan, 9 August 1860., 4 prints.
- Letter. John R. Bryan, Carysbrook, to Mrs. Georgia G. Grinnan, 16 January 1862., 2 prints.
- Letter. John R. Bryan, Carysbrook, to [?], 9 June 1868., 1 print.
- Letter. John R. Bryan, Lafitta, to Mrs. Andrew G. Grinnan, 14 December 1868., 2 prints.
- Letter. John R. Bryan, Lafitta, to Mrs. Georgia G. Grinnan, 1870., 2 prints.
- Letter. John R. Bryan, Carysbrook, to [?] Grinnan, 21 December 1871., 1 print.
- Letter. John R. Bryan, Richmond, to Dr. Andrew G. Grinnan, 14 March 1872., 2 prints.
- Letter. John R. Bryan, Carysbrook, to [?], 16 August 1872., 2 prints.
  Included are notes from another family member.
- Letter. John R. Bryan, New Orleans, to [?] Grinnan, 7 April 1874(?)., 2 prints.
- Letter. John R. Bryan, Carysbrook, to Dr. Andrew G. Grinnan, 29 April 1784(?)., 1 print.
- Letter. John R. Bryan, Richmond, to [?], 5 December 1874(?)., 1 print.
- Letter. John R. Bryan, Carysbrook, to Mrs. Andrew G. Grinnan, 6 April 1875., 2 prints.
- Letter. John R. Bryan, Carysbrook, [?], 2 February 1877., 1 print.
- Letter. John R. Bryan, Carysbrook, to [?], 9 February 1878., 1 print.
- Letter. John R. Bryan, Carysbrook, to [?] Grinnan, 16 April 1878., 2 prints.
- Letter. John R. Bryan, Carysbrook, to Mrs. Georgia G. Grinnan, 9 June 1879., 2 prints.
- Card. John M. Bryan to Dr. Andrew G. Grinnan, New York City, [March 17, 1882?]., print.
- Letter. John R. Bryan, University, to [?], 17 October 1883., 1 print.
- Letter. John R. Bryan, Fredericksburg, to Dr. Andrew G. Grinnan, 21 March 1884., 2 prints.
- Letter. John R. Bryan, Fredericksburg, [?], 3 October 1885., 2 prints.
- Letter. Frances Bland Coalter to Mrs. Davenportm Elm Grove near Staunton, [September 1809?]., 2 prints.
- Deed. Walter Crew and wife, Sarah and Samuel Cooper and wife, Susanna, to Charles Dabney, both parties of Hanover County, 15 acres in Hanover County., 1 print.
  Instrument is unsigned, undated, and does not include a date of recordation.
- Letter. John R. Bryan, Carysbrook, to [?], n.d., 2 prints.
- List of slaves., 3 prints.
- Dabney Family Bible records, 1756-1826., 3 prints.
- Bryan Family Bible records, 1708-1892., 12 prints.